Hello, I'm Chris on behalf of Team 7A.
Last week's pitch got us thinking:
Data alone doesn't move people. Today,
I'll show how the team progressed through
each phase of the double diamond design
process, what we learned from talking to
stakeholders and what our prototypes
taught us. In the discover phase,
we avoided yes/no or leading questions
and framed our enquiry with "how might
we" questions to surface real needs with
questions like "how might we engage the
user to interact with the QR code from
our poster?" From Sally, we heard that
current solutions were just graphs and
numbers and lacked human context.
Instead, she stressed, people really
respond to film/stories being told.
What we learned was that even with our
prototypes, which Sally really liked, we
still need to figure out a way to get
past the mental barriers of users of the
River Kelvin to interact with our
solutions. Next, in the Define
phase, we surface our mental models
explicitly by gathering what we learned
from the stakeholder meeting. We each
answered what matters most. raw accuracy
or emotional resonance. This exercise,
grounded in our shared mental models
exercises, help us avoid blind spots and
align on the true problem, making the
river condition both understandable and
compelling. Once we surfaced our
assumptions, we notice two conflicting
mental models. Model A, on-site and
on-sight, where people expect physical
glanceable warnings, and Model B,
remotely, where users want rich digital
content and community submissions. To
reconcile these, we turned to integrative
thinking. Rather than choosing one or the
other, we fused them. In our D
develop phase, we built a low-fidelity mix
of paper posters, prototype gauges, and a
QR-linked site where users could upload
sightings as stories or contribute to
warnings. We have since improved the
designs in our med to hi-fi prototyping
progression. Here is our physical story
poster and our story
digital counterpart.
And finally, our water information poster
and HiFi digital prototype with an AI
model to predict water levels. With
that, we set out to the River Kelvin for
field testing and usability scale.
We expected questions on chart clarity
and the data, but two elderly visitors
immediately scanned to read user stories
and noted they'd only scanned if they
told a narrative. Others said, "Put it
all on the poster!" to avoid scanning.
This tension between minimal friction and
rich storytelling reshaped our thinking.
So what we learned from building our
prototypes was that our reframed approach
uses eye-catching posters and gauges at
the rivers edge as the front door, with a
QR-linked story builder at the backend,
delivering both immediate visibility and
deeper digital engagement. From
presenting our prototypes to stakeholders
and actual river users, we learned 2
lessons. First, low-cost, "fail-fast"
mocks, surfaced what genuinely matters
far quicker than polished design.
Secondly, the experience - prototypes
that let people live the story. Imagining
a loved one at risk uncover emotional
drivers you can't see on static slides.
For example, even though there are
physical algae bloom warnings at the
river, a Glasgow dog owner had her dog
needing hospital attention after swimming
in the river. This personal experience
would prompt her empathy to participate
and scan the QR code to warn other users.
This insight will guide our next
iteration. In the Deliver
phase, our next-gen prototype is a mobile
story builder. Users scan a QR,
choose "add warning" or "share story",
then follow guided prompts to upload a
photo or text. Behind the scenes,
Friends of the River Kelvin curate
submissions with UK protocols to manage
liability. Finally, our AI model
fuses flow data with crowd stories to
provide short-term river risk
predictions, melding the data with human
context. We learned about the Glasgow
Penguins, an anonymous artist who placed
clay Penguins at the River Kelvin to
liven it up. It has since garnered a
large community following, prompting
users to seek them out at the River
Kelvin. This further reinforces what we
learned before, that users need that
story element. In the future, we'll pilot
at 5 sites, collaborate with Glasgow
Penguins for local flair and A/B test
poster only versus QR first. Our
metrics: Story contribution per visitor,
repeat engagement and ultimately fewer
safety incidents. Thank you for
listening and we can't wait to present to
you our final prototype solution during
the exhibition at GUU.